George Wellington Wilson Papers
George Wellington Wilson Papers
1893-1937
Wilson, George Wellington, 1870-1946.
2.0 linear ft.
Papers of the New York businessman and manager of fundraising events for Butler Lodge 504 of the Independent Order of Odd Fellows, South Butler, N.Y. Collection includes correspondence, financial records, photographs, broadsides and advertisements, reflecting Wilson's management of fraternal organization fund-raising events which included fairs, plays, minstrel shows, and various entertainments for the lodge.
148759
Biographical History
George W. Wilson (1870-1946) was a New York businessman and a member of Butler Lodge 504 of the Independent Order of Odd Fellows, South Butler, New York.
Wilson was born in Savannah in Wayne County, New York, to George Riley and Mary Ann (Gorham) Wilson. He attended Crusoe School in Savannah and later the South Butler Village School.
He married Florence Adella Niles on January 4, 1893 and the couple had two daughters, Addie Augusta (15 Oct 1893) and Valeria Ann (23 Sep 1895). Valeria later (24 Oct 1921) married George Parsons. Florence died August 8, 1821, and Wilson subsequently married Nettie May (Chapman) Johnson (died June 12, 1955).
In 1898 Wilson joined his brother, Gorham J. Wilson, in the Wilson Store in South Butler, and continued in this business until 1937. He was librarian and deacon of the Church of Christ, Disciples for many years, as well as president of the local fire company and the Sunday School Association. For fifty years he was a member of Butler Lodge 504 of the Independent Order of Odd Fellows, and was manager of the Lodge's fund-raising events for many years.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George W. Wilson Papers contain correspondence, financial records, notes, photographs, and published material. Most of the collection represents Mr. Wilson's management fund-raising events for Butler Lodge 504, including fairs, plays, minstrel shows, and various other entertainments.
Correspondence contains mostly incoming letters about future performances, ticket sales and business arrangements with theatrical agencies in Syracuse, New York, including Eastern Lyceum Bureau (1916-1918), Eastern-Empire Lyceum Bureau (1912-1914), and Royal Lyceum Bureau (1919-1923). There is also significant correspondence with the Clyde (New York) Opera House (1919-1922), Independent Order of Odd Fellows (1910-1916), New York State Department of Agriculture (1916), and the New York State Department of Farms and Markets, Division of Agriculture (1917-1918).
Financial records include a series of cashbooks, contracts with theatrical agencies, receipts, reports of the manager, tickets, and subscription forms.
Notes contain miscellaneous handwritten items about the Odd Fellows' fund-raising events, and there are a few Photographs.
Published material consists of advertisements, broadside playbills and programs for events in South Butler, New York.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Financial records are arranged alphabetically by type. Published material is arranged alphabetically by type.
Related Material
See also the
Central New York Cultural Ephemera Collection
and
Dave Salmon, Inc. Collection of Syracuse Cultural Ephemera
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Dance and theatre; New York State; Wilson, George Wellington, 1870-1946.; Independent Order of Odd Fellows.; Amusements -- Posters.; Businessmen -- New York (State) -- Wayne County.; Fraternal organizations -- New York (State); Printed ephemera.; Theatrical agencies -- New York (State); Wayne County (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Advertisements.; Broadsides (notices); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Playbills.; Programs (documents); Businessmen.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Gerald J. Parsons, 1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1893-1916; 1919-1937,; undated; 4 folders (Box 1)
- Financial records
  - Cashbooks, 1896-1924; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Contracts, Mar 1915-Jul 1924; printed material (Box 1)
  - Receipts, Jul 1903-Jan 1933 (Box 1)
  - Reports and statements, 1903; 1913-1919,; undated (Box 1)
  - Tickets and subscriptions, Dec 1900-Aug 1918; undated (Box 1)
- Notes
  - Independent Order of Odd Fellows, 1912-1916; 1929,; undated; list of committees for fairs (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Published material
  - Advertisements
    - Dona Walden, circa 1911?; correspondence (Box 2)
    - Empire Lyceum Bureau
      - 21 Dec 1911-1 Mar 1912, Otterbein Male Quartet, Willard Gorton, Aylesworth Sisters, G.A. Morris, The Tennesseans (Box 2)
      - circa 1912-1913, C. Lawrence Abbott, Brewer Concert Entertainers, Herbert A. and Floy Mahan Sprague (Box 2)
      - circa 1912-1914, Alvah Green, Yare Duo, Washington Brothers' Alabama Jubilee Quartet (Box 2)
      - 1914?, Brewer Concert Entertainers, Mr. and Mrs. Hewitt Milton Marsh (Box 2)
    - Eastern-Empire Lyceum Bureau
      - 1915, Alfred R. Burke, Maynard Lee Daggy, Griswold Sisters Quartet (Box 2)
      - Mar? 1915, Chicago Concert Party, Famous Suwanee River Quartette, Litchfield Latimer Duo, Mason's Jubilee Singers, Ray Newton, Grace and James Potter, Gamil Saldanha, Herbert A. and Floy Mahan Sprague (Box 2)
      - circa 1915?, Athenian Jubilee Trio, Bay State Entertainers, the Ithacans, Galen Ross, the Wassere (Box 2)
      - circa 1915?, Merritt B. Holley, Old Kentucky Jubilee Quartet, Stockholm Concert Company; undated notes (Box 2)
      - circa 1915?, Emil Closs, Elite Trio (Box 2)
      - circa 1915?, S. Platt Jones, Catherine Kennedy (Box 2)
      - 15 Oct 1915-10 Feb 1916, Elite Trio, Morris Gershon, Harmony Trio, Lowry-Lawrence Entertainers (Box 2)
    - Eastern Lyceum Bureau
      - 26 Oct 1916-12 Feb 1917, Merry Musical Maids, Maynard Lee Daggy, Venetian Trio (Box 2)
      - circa 1916-1917?, Moon Young Chun, Florence Josephine Ensworth, Willard Gorton, Alfred R. Burke, Rufu Everson King (Box 2)
      - circa 1916-1917?, The American Girls (Box 2)
    - Royal Lyceum Bureau
      - 1919, Belle F. Dickery, Clarence Oliver Moore, National Male Quartet, Purushottam Bhikajee Mulye, Lewis and Theda Parmenter, Ted Warner, Winslow Concert Company (Box 2)
      - Undated, Bud Fisher's Mutt and Jeff Cartoon Musical Comedy (Box 2)
      - Undated, William Charles and Harriet Vogel Lowe Concert and Entertainment Company (Box 2)
      - Undated, Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Broadsides
    - "Davis' Hall...Genevieve Wilson...with Mr. G. E. Wilson...Valley Farm, or, The Power of True Love", 1910 (Box 2)
    - "Modern Hippodrome Shows", undated (Box 2)
    - "R. W. Marks presents May Bell Marks in her Original Character Sketches", undated (Box 2)
    - "Dona Walden and Co....Master Magician", undated (Box 2)
    - "Big Fair...Feb 20-23...Entertainment...by Brown and Lyn Colored Minstrels", 1929 (Oversize 1)
    - "Coming! The Star Dramatic Company! Who will present their great five-act drama, Broken Promises", undated (Oversize 1)
    - "Hill's Moving Pictures...prsenting Russian-Japanese War...The Great Train Robbery...", undated (Oversize 1)
    - I.O.O.F. Fair, South Butler, Mar 13-18, 1911 (Oversize 1)
    - Jones' Picture and Vaudeville Entertainers, undated (Oversize 1)
    - "The Modern Shows...Lackland and Lackland...", undated (Oversize 1)
    - Passion Play, the Life of Christ, 5 Jun 1908 (Oversize 1)
    - "Walden...Magic Illusions...", undated (Oversize 1)
  - Programs
    - May 1915-Dec 1928, undated (Box 2)